In this video, we'll talk about
在这段视频中 我们将讨论
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
the second major type of machine
第二种主要的机器学习问题
learning problem, called Unsupervised Learning.
叫做无监督学习
In the last video, we talked about Supervised Learning.
在上一节视频中 我们已经讲过了监督学习
Back then, recall data sets
回想起上次的数据集
that look like this, where each
每个样本
example was labeled either
都已经被标明为
as a positive or negative example,
正样本或者负样本
whether it was a benign or a malignant tumor.
即良性或恶性肿瘤
So for each example in Supervised
因此 对于监督学习中的每一个样本
Learning, we were told explicitly what
我们已经被清楚地告知了
is the so-called right answer,
什么是所谓的正确答案
whether it's benign or malignant.
即它们是良性还是恶性
In Unsupervised Learning, we're given
在无监督学习中
data that looks different
我们用的数据会和监督学习里的看起来有些不一样
than data that looks like
在无监督学习中
this that doesn't have
没有属性或标签这一概念
any labels or that all
也就是说所有的数据
has the same label or really no labels.
都是一样的 没有区别
So we're given the data set and
所以在无监督学习中 我们只有一个数据集
we're not told what to
没人告诉我们该怎么做
do with it and we're not
我们也不知道
told what each data point is.
每个数据点究竟是什么意思
Instead we're just told, here is a data set.
相反 它只告诉我们 现在有一个数据集
Can you find some structure in the data?
你能在其中找到某种结构吗？
Given this data set, an
对于给定的数据集
Unsupervised Learning algorithm might decide that
无监督学习算法可能判定
the data lives in two different clusters.
该数据集包含两个不同的聚类
And so there's one cluster
你看 这是第一个聚类
and there's a different cluster.
然后这是另一个聚类
And yes, Supervised Learning algorithm may
你猜对了 无监督学习算法
break these data into these two separate clusters.
会把这些数据分成两个不同的聚类
So this is called a clustering algorithm.
所以这就是所谓的聚类算法
And this turns out to be used in many places.
实际上它被用在许多地方
One example where clustering
我们来举一个聚类算法的栗子
is used is in Google
Google 新闻的例子
News and if you have not
如果你还没见过这个页面的话
seen this before, you can actually
你可以到这个URL
go to this URL news.google.com
news.google.com
to take a look.
去看看
What Google News does is everyday
谷歌新闻每天都在干什么呢？
it goes and looks at tens
他们每天会去收集
of thousands or hundreds of
成千上万的
thousands of new stories on the
网络上的新闻
web and it groups them into cohesive news stories.
然后将他们分组 组成一个个新闻专题
For example, let's look here.
比如 让我们来看看这里
The URLs here link
这里的URL链接
to different news stories
连接着不同的
about the BP Oil Well story.
有关BP油井事故的报道
So, let's click on
所以 让我们点击
one of these URL's and we'll
这些URL中的一个
click on one of these URL's.
恩 让我们点一个
What I'll get to is a web page like this.
然后我们会来到这样一个网页
Here's a Wall Street
这是一篇来自华尔街日报的
Journal article about, you know, the BP
有关……你懂的
Oil Well Spill stories of
有关BP油井泄漏事故的报道
"BP Kills Macondo",
标题为《BP杀死了Macondo》
which is a name of the
Macondo 是个地名
spill and if you
就是那个漏油事故的地方
click on a different URL
如果你从这个组里点击一个不同的URL
from that group then you might get the different story.
那么你可能会得到不同的新闻
Here's the CNN story about a
这里是一则CNN的新闻
game, the BP Oil Spill,
是一个有关BP石油泄漏的视频
and if you click on yet
如果你再点击第三个链接
a third link, then you might get a different story.
又会出现不同的新闻
Here's the UK Guardian story
这边是英国卫报的报道
about the BP Oil Spill.
也是关于BP石油泄漏
So what Google News has done
所以 谷歌新闻所做的就是
is look for tens of thousands of
去搜索成千上万条新闻
news stories and automatically cluster them together.
然后自动的将他们聚合在一起
So, the news stories that are all
因此 有关同一主题的
about the same topic get displayed together.
新闻被显示在一起
It turns out that
其实
clustering algorithms and Unsupervised Learning
聚类算法和无监督学习算法
algorithms are used in many other problems as well.
也可以被用于许多其他的问题
Here's one on understanding genomics.
这里我们举个它在基因组学中的应用
Here's an example of DNA microarray data.
下面是一个关于基因芯片的例子
The idea is put
基本的思想是
a group of different individuals and
给定一组不同的个体
for each of them, you measure
对于每个个体
how much they do or do not have a certain gene.
检测它们是否拥有某个特定的基因
Technically you measure how much certain genes are expressed.
也就是说，你要去分析有多少基因显现出来了
So these colors, red, green,
因此 这些颜色 红 绿
gray and so on, they
灰 等等 它们
show the degree to which
展示了这些不同的个体
different individuals do or
是否拥有一个特定基因
do not have a specific gene.
的不同程度
And what you can do is then
然后你所能做的就是
run a clustering algorithm to group
运行一个聚类算法
individuals into different categories
把不同的个体归入不同的类
or into different types of people.
或归为不同类型的人
So this is Unsupervised Learning because
这就是无监督学习
we're not telling the algorithm in advance
我们没有提前告知这个算法
that these are type 1 people,
这些是第一类的人
those are type 2 persons, those
这些是第二类的人
are type 3 persons and so
这些是第三类的人等等
on and instead what were saying is yeah here's a bunch of data.
相反我们只是告诉算法 你看 这儿有一堆数据
I don't know what's in this data.
我不知道这个数据是什么东东
I don't know who's and what type.
我不知道里面都有些什么类型 叫什么名字
I don't even know what the different
我甚至不知道都有哪些类型
types of people are, but can
但是
you automatically find structure in
请问你可以自动的找到这些数据中的类型吗？
the data from the you automatically
然后自动的
cluster the individuals into these types
按得到的类型把这些个体分类
that I don't know in advance?
虽然事先我并不知道哪些类型
Because we're not giving the algorithm
因为对于这些数据样本来说
the right answer for the
我们没有给算法一个
examples in my data
正确答案
set, this is Unsupervised Learning.
所以 这就是无监督学习
Unsupervised Learning or clustering is used for a bunch of other applications.
无监督学习或聚类算法在其他领域也有着大量的应用
It's used to organize large computer clusters.
它被用来组织大型的计算机集群
I had some friends looking at
我有一些朋友在管理
large data centers, that is
大型数据中心 也就是
large computer clusters and trying
大型计算机集群 并试图
to figure out which machines tend to
找出哪些机器趋向于
work together and if
协同工作
you can put those machines together,
如果你把这些机器放在一起
you can make your data center work more efficiently.
你就可以让你的数据中心更高效地工作
This second application is on social network analysis.
第二种应用是用于社交网络的分析
So given knowledge about which friends
所以 如果可以得知
you email the most or
哪些朋友你用email联系的最多
given your Facebook friends or
或者知道你的Facebook好友
your Google+ circles, can
或者你Google+里的朋友
we automatically identify which are
知道了这些之后
cohesive groups of friends,
我们是否可以自动识别
also which are groups of people
哪些是很要好的朋友组
that all know each other?
哪些仅仅是互相认识的朋友组
Market segmentation.
还有在市场分割中的应用
Many companies have huge databases of customer information.
许多公司拥有庞大的客户信息数据库
So, can you look at this
那么 给你一个
customer data set and automatically
客户数据集 你能否
discover market segments and automatically
自动找出不同的市场分割
group your customers into different
并自动将你的客户分到不同的
market segments so that
细分市场中
you can automatically and more
从而有助于我在
efficiently sell or market
不同的细分市场中
your different market segments together?
进行更有效的销售
Again, this is Unsupervised Learning
这也是无监督学习
because we have all this
我们现在有
customer data, but we don't
这些客户数据
know in advance what are the
但我们预先并不知道
market segments and for
有哪些细分市场
the customers in our data
而且
set, you know, we don't know in
对于我们数据集的某个客户
advance who is in
我们也不能预先知道
market segment one, who is
谁属于细分市场一
in market segment two, and so on.
谁又属于细分市场二等等
But we have to let the algorithm discover all this just from the data.
但我们必须让这个算法自己去从数据中发现这一切
Finally, it turns out that Unsupervised
最后
Learning is also used for
事实上无监督学习也被用于
surprisingly astronomical data analysis
天文数据分析
and these clustering algorithms gives
通过这些聚类算法 我们发现了许多
surprisingly interesting useful theories
惊人的、有趣的 以及实用的
of how galaxies are born.
关于星系是如何诞生的理论
All of these are examples of clustering,
所有这些都是聚类算法的例子
which is just one type of Unsupervised Learning.
而聚类只是无监督学习的一种
Let me tell you about another one.
现在让我来告诉你另一种
I'm gonna tell you about the cocktail party problem.
我先来介绍一下鸡尾酒宴问题
So, you've been to cocktail parties before, right?
恩 我想你参加过鸡尾酒会的 是吧？
Well, you can imagine there's a
嗯 想象一下
party, room full of people, all
有一个宴会 有一屋子的人
sitting around, all talking at the
大家都坐在一起
same time and there are
而且在同时说话
all these overlapping voices because everyone
有许多声音混杂在一起
is talking at the same time, and
因为每个人都是在同一时间说话的
it is almost hard to hear the person in front of you.
在这种情况下你很难听清楚你面前的人说的话
So maybe at a
因此 比如有这样一个场景
cocktail party with two people,
宴会上只有两个人
two people talking at the same
两个人
time, and it's a somewhat
同时说话
small cocktail party.
恩 这是个很小的鸡尾酒宴会
And we're going to put two
我们准备好了两个麦克风
microphones in the room so
把它们放在房间里
there are microphones, and because
然后
these microphones are at two
因为这两个麦克风距离这两个人
different distances from the
的距离是不同的
speakers, each microphone records
每个麦克风都记录下了
a different combination of these two speaker voices.
来自两个人的声音的不同组合
Maybe speaker one is a
也许A的声音
little louder in microphone one
在第一个麦克风里的声音会响一点
and maybe speaker two is a
也许B的声音
little bit louder on microphone 2
在第二个麦克风里会比较响一些
because the 2 microphones are
因为2个麦克风
at different positions relative to
的位置相对于
the 2 speakers, but each
2个说话者的位置是不同的
microphone would cause an overlapping
但每个麦克风都会录到
combination of both speakers' voices.
来自两个说话者的重叠部分的声音
So here's an actual recording
这里有一个
of two speakers recorded by a researcher.
来自一个研究员录下的两个说话者的声音
Let me play for you the
让我先放给你听第一个
first, what the first microphone sounds like.
这是第一个麦克风录到的录音：
One (uno), two (dos),
一 (UNO)  二 (DOS)
three (tres), four (cuatro), five
三 (TRES)  四 (CUATRO)  五 (CINCO)
(cinco), six (seis), seven (siete),
六 (SEIS)  七 (SIETE)
eight (ocho), nine (nueve), ten (y diez).
八 (ocho)  九 (NUEVE)  十 (Y DIEZ)
All right, maybe not the most interesting cocktail
好吧 这大概不是什么有趣的酒会……
party, there's two people
……在这个酒会上 有两个人
counting from one to ten
各自从1数到10
in two languages but you know.
但用的是两种不同语言
What you just heard was the
你刚才听到的是
first microphone recording, here's the second recording.
第一个麦克风的录音 这里是第二个的：
Uno (one), dos (two), tres (three), cuatro
一 (UNO)  二 (DOS)  三 (TRES)
(four), cinco (five), seis (six), siete (seven),
四 (CUATRO) 五 (CINCO)  六 (SEIS)  七 (SIETE)
ocho (eight), nueve (nine) y diez (ten).
八 (ocho) 九 (NUEVE)  十 (Y DIEZ)
So we can do, is take
所以 我们能做的就是把
these two microphone recorders and give
这两个录音输入
them to an Unsupervised Learning algorithm
一种无监督学习算法中
called the cocktail party algorithm,
称为“鸡尾酒会算法”
and tell the algorithm
让这个算法
- find structure in this data for you.
帮你找出其中蕴含的分类
And what the algorithm will do
然后这个算法
is listen to these
就会去听这些
audio recordings and say, you
录音 并且你知道
know it sounds like the
这听起​​来像
two audio recordings are being
两个音频录音
added together or that have being
被叠加在一起
summed together to produce these recordings that we had.
所以我们才能听到这样的效果
Moreover, what the cocktail party
此外 这个算法
algorithm will do is separate
还会分离出
out these two audio sources
这两个被
that were being added or being
叠加到一起的
summed together to form other
音频源
recordings and, in fact,
事实上
here's the first output of the cocktail party algorithm.
这是我们的鸡尾酒会算法的第一个输出
One, two, three, four,
一 二 三 四
five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
五 六 七 八 九 十
So, I separated out the English
所以我在一个录音中
voice in one of the recordings.
分离出了英文声音
And here's the second of it.
这是第二个输出
Uno, dos, tres, quatro, cinco,
Uno dos tres quatro cinco
seis, siete, ocho, nueve y diez.
seis siete ocho nueve y diez
Not too bad, to give you
听起来不错嘛
one more example, here's another
再举一个例子 这是另一个录音
recording of another similar situation,
也是在一个类似的场景下
here's the first microphone :  One,
这是第一个麦克风的录音：
two, three, four, five, six,
一 二 三 四 五 六
seven, eight, nine, ten.
七 八 九 十
OK so the poor guy's gone
OK 这个可怜的家伙从
home from the cocktail party and
鸡尾酒会回家了
he 's now sitting in a room by himself talking to his radio.
他现在独自一人坐在屋里 对着录音机自言自语
Here's the second microphone recording.
这是第二个麦克风的录音
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
一 二 三 四 五 六 七 八 九 十
When you give these two microphone
当你把这两个麦克风录音
recordings to the same algorithm,
送给与刚刚相同的算法处理
what it does, is again say,
它所做的还是
you know, it sounds like there
告诉你 这听起来有
are two audio sources, and moreover,
两种音频源 并且
the album says, here is
算法说
the first of the audio sources I found.
这里是我找到的第一个音频源
One, two, three, four,
一 二 三 四
five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
五 六 七 八 九 十
So that wasn't perfect, it
恩 不是太完美
got the voice, but it
提取到了人声
also got a little bit of the music in there.
但还有一点音乐没有剔除掉
Then here's the second output to the algorithm.
这是算法的第二个输出
Not too bad, in that second
还好 在第二个输出中
output it managed to get rid of the voice entirely.
它设法剔除掉了整个人声
And just, you know,
只是清理了下音乐
cleaned up the music, got rid of the counting from one to ten.
剔除了从一到十的计数
So you might look at
所以 你可以看到
an Unsupervised Learning algorithm like
像这样的无监督学习算法
this and ask how
也许你想问 要实现这样的算法
complicated this is to implement this, right?
很复杂吧？
It seems like in order to,
看起来 为了
you know, build this application, it seems
构建这个应用程序
like to do this audio processing you
做这个音频处理
need to write a ton of code
似乎需要写好多代码啊
or maybe link into like a
或者需要链接到
bunch of synthesizer Java libraries that
一堆处理音频的Java库
process audio, seems like
貌似需要一个
a really complicated program, to do
非常复杂的程序
this audio, separating out audio and so on.
分离出音频等
It turns out the algorithm, to
实际上
do what you just heard, that
要实现你刚刚听到的效果
can be done with one line
只需要一行代码就可以了
of code - shown right here.
写在这里呢
It take researchers a long
当然 研究人员
time to come up with this line of code.
花了很长时间才想出这行代码的 ^-^
I'm not saying this is an easy problem,
我不是说这是一个简单的问题
But it turns out that when you
但事实上 如果你
use the right programming environment, many learning
使用正确的编程环境 许多学习
algorithms can be really short programs.
算法是用很短的代码写出来的
So this is also why in
所以这也是为什么在
this class we're going to
这门课中我们要
use the Octave programming environment.
使用Octave的编程环境
Octave, is free open source
Octave是一个免费的
software, and using a
开放源码的软件
tool like Octave or Matlab,
使用Octave或Matlab这类的工具
many learning algorithms become just
许多学习算法
a few lines of code to implement.
都可以用几行代码就可以实现
Later in this class, I'll just teach
在后续课程中
you a little bit about how to
我会教你如何使用Octave
use Octave and you'll be
你会学到
implementing some of these algorithms in Octave.
如何在Octave中实现这些算法
Or if you have Matlab you can use that too.
或者 如果你有Matlab 你可以用它
It turns out the Silicon Valley, for
事实上 在硅谷
a lot of machine learning algorithms,
很多的机器学习算法
what we do is first prototype
我们都是先用Octave
our software in Octave because software
写一个程序原型
in Octave makes it incredibly fast
因为在Octave中实现这些
to implement these learning algorithms.
学习算法的速度快得让你无法想象
Here each of these functions
在这里 每一个函数
like for example the SVD
例如 SVD
function that stands for singular
意思是奇异值分解
value decomposition; but that turns
但这其实是解线性方程
out to be a
的一个惯例
linear algebra routine, that is just built into Octave.
它被内置在Octave软件中了
If you were trying to do this
如果你试图
in C++ or Java,
在C + +或Java中做这个
this would be many many lines of
将需要写N多代码
code linking complex C++ or Java libraries.
并且还要连接复杂的C + +或Java库
So, you can implement this stuff as
所以 你可以在C++或
C++ or Java
Java或Python中
or Python, it's just much
实现这个算法 只是会
more complicated to do so in those languages.
更加复杂而已
What I've seen after having taught
在教授机器学习
machine learning for almost a
将近10年后
decade now, is that, you
我得出的一个经验就是
learn much faster if you
如果你使用Octave的话
use Octave as your
会学的更快
programming environment, and if
并且如果你用
you use Octave as your
Octave作为你的学习工具
learning tool and as your
和开发原型的工具
prototyping tool, it'll let
你的学习和开发过程
you learn and prototype learning algorithms much more quickly.
会变得更快
And in fact what many people will
而事实上在硅谷
do to in the large Silicon
很多人会这样做
Valley companies is in fact, use
他们会先用Octave
an algorithm like Octave to first
来实现这样一个学习算法原型
prototype the learning algorithm, and
只有在确定
only after you've gotten it
这个算法可以工作后
to work, then you migrate
才开始迁移到
it to C++ or Java or whatever.
C++ Java或其它编译环境
It turns out that by doing
事实证明 这样做
things this way, you can often
实现的算法
get your algorithm to work much
比你一开始就用C++
faster than if you were starting out in C++.
实现的算法要快多了
So, I know that as an
所以 我知道
instructor, I get to
作为一个老师
say "trust me on
我不能老是念叨：
this one" only a finite
“在这个问题上相信我“
number of times, but for
但对于
those of you who've never used these
那些从来没有用过这种
Octave type programming environments before,
类似Octave的编程环境的童鞋
I am going to ask you
我还是要请你
to trust me on this one,
相信我这一次
and say that you, you will,
我认为
I think your time, your development
你的时间 研发时间
time is one of the most valuable resources.
是你最宝贵的资源之一
And having seen lots
当见过很多的人这样做以后
of people do this, I think
我觉得如果你也这样做
you as a machine learning
作为一个机器学习的
researcher, or machine learning developer
研究者和开发者
will be much more productive if
你会更有效率
you learn to start in prototype,
如果你学会先用Octave开发原型
to start in Octave, in some other language.
而不是先用其他的编程语言来开发
Finally, to wrap
最后 总结一下
up this video, I have one quick review question for you.
这里有一个问题需要你来解答
We talked about Unsupervised Learning, which
我们谈到了无监督学习
is a learning setting where you
它是一种学习机制
give the algorithm a ton
你给算法大量的数据
of data and just ask it
要求它找出数据中
to find structure in the data for us.
蕴含的类型结构
Of the following four examples, which
以下的四个例子中
ones, which of these four
哪一个
do you think would will be
您认为是
an Unsupervised Learning algorithm as
无监督学习算法
opposed to Supervised Learning problem.
而不是监督学习问题
For each of the four
对于每一个选项
check boxes on the left,
在左边的复选框
check the ones for which
选中你认为
you think Unsupervised Learning
属于无监督学习的
algorithm would be appropriate and
选项
then click the button on the lower right to check your answer.
然后按一下右下角的按钮 提交你的答案
So when the video pauses, please
所以 当视频暂停时
answer the question on the slide.
请回答幻灯片上的这个问题
So, hopefully, you've remembered the spam folder problem.
恩 没忘记垃圾邮件文件夹问题吧？
If you have labeled data, you
如果你已经标记过数据
know, with spam and
那么就有垃圾邮件和
non-spam e-mail, we'd treat this as a Supervised Learning problem.
非垃圾邮件的区别 我们会将此视为一个监督学习问题
The news story example, that's
新闻故事的例子
exactly the Google News example
正是我们在本课中讲到的
that we saw in this video,
谷歌新闻的例子
we saw how you can use
我们介绍了你可以如何使用
a clustering algorithm to cluster
聚类算法这些文章聚合在一起
these articles together so that's Unsupervised Learning.
所以这是无监督学习问题
The market segmentation example I
市场细分的例子
talked a little bit earlier, you
我之前有说过
can do that as an Unsupervised Learning problem
这也是一个无监督学习问题
because I am just gonna
因为我是要
get my algorithm data and ask
拿到数据 然后要求
it to discover market segments automatically.
它自动发现细分市场
And the final example, diabetes, well,
最后一个例子 糖尿病
that's actually just like our
这实际上就像我们
breast cancer example from the last video.
上节课讲到的乳腺癌的例子
Only instead of, you know,
只不过这里不是
good and bad cancer tumors or
好的或坏的癌细胞
benign or malignant tumors we
良性或恶性肿瘤我们
instead have diabetes or
现在是有糖尿病或
not and so we will
没有糖尿病 所以这是
use that as a supervised,
有监督的学习问题
we will solve that as
像处理那个乳腺癌的问题一样
a Supervised Learning problem just like
我们会把它作为一个
we did for the breast tumor data.
有监督的学习问题来处理
So, that's it for Unsupervised
好了 关于无监督学习问题
Learning and in the
就讲这么多了
next video, we'll delve more
下一节课中我们
into specific learning algorithms
会涉及到更具体的学习算法
and start to talk about
并开始讨论
just how these algorithms work and
这些算法是如何工作的
how we can, how you can go about implementing them.
以及我们如何来实现它们